About 15 years ago, I went to visit a friend in Hong Kong.
قبل حوالي ١٥ سنة مضت، ذهبت لزيارة صديق في هونق كونق
And at the time I was very superstitious.
وفي ذاك الوقت كنت أؤمن بالخرافات كثيراً
So, upon landing -- this was still at the old Hong Kong airport
لذا خلال نزول الطائرة.. ذلك كان سابقاً في مطار هونق كونق القديم
that's Kai Tak, when it was smack in the middle of the city --
الذي يدعى كاي تاك، وكان في وسط المدينة..
I thought, "If I see something good, I'm going to have a great time here in
راودتني فكرة، إذا رأيت شيئاً جيداً فذلك سيعني بأنني سأقضي وقتاً رائع
my two weeks. And if I see something negative, I'm going to be miserable, indeed."
في الأسبوعين التاليين. وأما إذا رأيت شيئاً سلبياً، فإنني سأكون تعيساً بلا شك
So the plane landed in between the buildings
وهبطت الطائرة وسط المباني
and got to a full stop in front of this little billboard.
وتوقفت بالضبط أمام هذه اللافتة الصغيرة. "فائز"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I actually went to see some of the design companies
وفي الحقيقة ذهبت لرؤية بعض شركات التصاميم
in Hong Kong in my stay there.
في هونق كونق خلال تلك الزيارة
And it turned out that --
واتضح لي حينها..
I just went to see, you know, what they are doing in Hong Kong.
تعلمون، ذهبت لأستطلع ما كانوا يصنعون في هونق كونق
But I actually walked away with a great job offer.
ولكنني رجعت بفرصة عمل عظيمة
And I flew back to Austria, packed my bags,
ورجعت إلى النمسا لأوضب أغراضي
and, another week later, I was again on my way to Hong Kong
وبعدها بأسبوع، كنت مرة أخرى في طريقي إلى هونق كونق
still superstitions and thinking, "Well, if that 'Winner' billboard is still up,
وكنت لازلت أفكر بأشياء خرافية قائلاً لنفسي: إذا كانت لافتة "فائز" لا تزال في مكانها
I'm going to have a good time working here.
فسأقضي وقتاً جيداً في عملي هناك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if it's gone, it's going to be really miserable and stressful."
أما إذا كانت قد أزيلت فسأقضي وقتاً بائساً ومليئاً بالضغوطات
So it turned out that not only was the billboard still up
ومن ثم اتضح بأنه ليست تلك اللافته موجودة فقط
but they had put this one right next to it.
بل وضعوا هذه الأخرى بجنبها أيضاً. "ضعف السعادة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
On the other hand, it also taught me where superstition gets me
ومن جهة أخرى تعلمت إلى أين يوصلني إيماني بالخرافات
because I really had a terrible time in Hong Kong.
فقد قضيت وقتاً مريعاً حقاً في هونق كونق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
However, I did have a number of real moments of happiness in my life --
ولكن حظيت بلحظات من السعادة في حياتي..
of, you know, I think what the conference brochure refers to
كما تعلمون، أظن بأن كتيب المحاضرة يشير إليها
as "moments that take your breath away."
كلحظات تأخذ الأنفاس
And since I'm a big list maker, I actually listed them all.
وبما أنني أحب كتابة القائمات جداً، فقد وضعت كل هذه اللحظات في قائمة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, you don't have to go through the trouble of reading them
ليس عليكم الآن بأن ترهقوا أنفسكم بقراءتها
and I won't read them for you.
كما أنني لن أقرأها لكم
I know that it's incredibly boring to hear about other people's happinesses.
أعلم بأنه من الممل بشكل فضيع أن تسمع عن سعادة غيرك من الناس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What I did do, though is, I actually looked at them from a design standpoint
ما فعلته بعدها هو أنني نظرت إلى القائمة من منظوري كمصمم
and just eliminated all the ones that had nothing to do with design.
وعزلت كل ما ليس له علاقة بالتصميم
And, very surprisingly, over half of them had, actually, something to do with design.
وبشكل مفاجئ جداً، وجدت في الحقيقة بأن أكثر من نصفهم كان له علاقة بالتصميم
So there are, of course, two different possibilities.
وهناك بالطبع احتمالين مختلفين
There's one from a consumer's point of view --
هناك احتمال من وجهة نظر المستهلك...
where I was happy while experiencing design.
حيث كنت سعيداً بتجربة التصميم
And I'll just give you one example. I had gotten my first Walkman.
وسأعطيكم مثالاً واحداً فقط. كنت قد حضيت بأول جهاز ووكمان لي
This is 1983.
كان ذلك في ١٩٨٣
My brother had this great Yamaha motorcycle
كان لأخي دراجة ياماها النارية
that he was willing to borrow to me freely.
والتي كان مستعداً لأعارتي إياها وقتما شئت
And The Police's "Synchronicity"
وكان شريط كاسيت "سينكرونسيتي" لـفرقة "ذا بوليس"
cassette had just been released
قد نزل في الأسواق حينها
and there was no helmet law in my hometown of Bregenz.
ولم يكن في مدينتي "بريجينز" قانون يجبر على لبس خوذة الدراجة
So you could drive up into the mountains
لذا كان يمكنك قيادة الدراجة عند الجبال بحرية
freely blasting The Police on the new Sony Walkman.
والاستمتاع بسماع أغاني "ذا بوليس" بجهاز سوني ووكمان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I remember it as a true moment of happiness.
وأتذكر هذا الموقف كلحظة سعادة حقيقية
You know, of course, they are related to this combination of
كما ترون فإن اللحظة متصلة بمجموعة متكونة
at least two of them being, you know, design objects.
على الأقل من سلعة أو أكثر من السلع المصممة
And, you know, there's a scale of happiness when you talk about in design
وتعلمون، هناك مقياس للسعادة عندما نتكلم عنها من ناحية التصميم
but the motorcycle incident would definitely be, you know,
لكن موقف الدراجة النارية فسأصنفه في هذه الخانة..
situated somewhere here -- right in there between Delight and Bliss.
بالضبط هنا بين البهجة والهناء
Now, there is the other part, from a designer's standpoint --
وهناك الجزء الآخر، من وجهة نظر المصمم..
if you're happy while actually doing it.
إذا كنت سعيداً بقيامك بالتصميم
And one way to see how happy designers are when they're designing could be to
و قد تكون من طرق معرفة إذا ما كان المصمم سعيداً في عمله
look at the authors' photos on the back of their monographs?
بأن تنظر إلى صورته في آخر الرسالة العلمية المكتوبة عنه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, according to this, the Australians and the Japanese
ونسبة إلى هذه الطريقة فإن المصممين الأستراليين واليابانيين
as well as the Mexicans
وكذلك المكسيكيين
are very happy.
سعداء جداً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
While, somewhat, the Spaniards ...
وبينما في المقابل، فإن الإسبان..
and, I think, particularly, the Swiss
والسويسريين كما أظن
(Laughter),
(ضحك)
don't seem to be doing all that well.
ليسوا كذلك تماماً
Last November, a museum opened in Tokyo called The Mori Museum,
في شهر نوفمبر الماضي، افتتح متحف في طوكيو، يدعى متحف "موري"
in a skyscraper, up on the 56th floor.
في ناطحة سحاب، في الطابق السادس والخمسين
And their inaugural exhibit was called "Happiness."
ومعرضهم الافتتاحي كان بعنوان "السعادة"
And I went, very eagerly, to see it, because --
وذهبت بفضول كبير لأرى، لأنه..
well, also, with an eye on this conference.
حسناً، لسبب يتعلق بهذه المحاضرة
And they interestingly sectioned the exhibit off into four different areas.
وكانوا قد قسموا المعرض بشكل مثير للاهتمام إلى ٤ أقسام مختلفة
Under "Arcadia," they showed things like this, from the Edo period --
تحت قسم "أركاديا" عرضوا أشياء مثل هذه، من عهد الإيدو..
a hundred ways to write "happiness" in different forms.
مئة طريقة لكتابة "سعادة" بأشكال متعددة
Or they had this apple by Yoko Ono -- that, of course, later on
وعرضوا هذه التفاحة بصنع يوكو أونو.. والتي كما تعلمون بالطبع
was, you know, made into the label for The Beatles.
تحولت إلى شعار "ذا بيتلز"
Under "Nirvana" they showed this Constable painting.
وتحت قسم "نيرفانا" عرضوا هذه اللوحة لـ"كونستيبل"
And there was a little -- an interesting theory about abstraction.
وكان هناك القليل من... نظرية مثيرة عن الفن التجريدي
This is a blue field -- it's actually an Yves Klein painting.
وهذه مساحة زرقاء.. في الواقع هي لوحة لـ"إيفز لاين"
And the theory was that if you abstract an image, you really, you know
وكانت النظرية تنص على أنك إذا مثلت صورة تجريدياً، فإنك في الحقيقة
open as much room for the un-representable --
تفتح مساحة لا محدودة لما لا يمكن عرضه..
and, therefore, you know, are able to involve the viewer more.
وبذلك، تصبح قادراً على دمج المشاهد أكثر
Then, under "Desire," they showed these Shunsho paintings --
ومن ثم تحت قسم "ديزاير" (بمعنى الرغبة)، عرضوا هذه اللوحات من "شونشو"..
also from the Edo period -- ink on silk.
كذلك من عهد الإيدو.. حبر على حرير
And, lastly, under "Harmony," they had this 13th-century mandala from Tibet.
وآخيراً تحت قسم "هارموني" (بمعنى التناغم)، عرضوا هذه الماندالا من القرن الثالث عشر من التبت
Now, what I took away from the exhibit was that
والآن، ربما ما لاحظته في زيارتي للمعرض هو
maybe with the exception of the mandala
أن معظم القطع الفنية، باستثناء الماندالا
most of the pieces in there were actually about the visualization of happiness
كانوا في الحقيقة عن تصور السعادة
and not about happiness.
ولم يكونوا عن السعادة ذاتها
And I felt a little bit cheated, because the visualization --
وأحسست بأنيي قد خذلت، لأن التصور..
that's a really easy thing to do.
شيءٌ سهل التطبيق
And, you know, my studio -- we've done it all the time.
وتعلمون، في الستوديو... نطبق هذا الشيء طوال الوقت
This is, you know, a book.
مثلاً نأخذ هذا الكتاب
A happy dog -- and you take it out, it's an aggressive dog.
هذا كلب سعيد.. من ثم كلب عدائي
It's a happy David Byrne and an angry David Byrne.
وهذا ديفيد بايرن سعيد، وهذا ديفيد بايرن غاضب
Or a jazz poster with a happy face and a more aggressive face.
وهذا ملصق للجاز عليه وجه سعيد وآخر عدائي أكثر
You know, that's not a big deal to accomplish.
تعلمون، هذا ليس بالشيء الصعب للتطبيق
It has gotten to the point where, you know, within advertising
لقد وصل الموضوع إلى حد بأنه في الدعايات
or within the movie industry, "happy" has gotten such a bad reputation that
أو في مجال الأفلام، أخذت "السعادة" سمعةً سيئةً لدرجة
if you actually want to do something with the subject
بأنك إذا أردت بأن تظهر بمظهر أصلي
and still appear authentic, you almost would have to, you know,
وأنت تصنع شيء يتعلق بالموضوع، فإنك تقريباً تضطر
do it from a cynical point of view.
لصنعه من وجهة نظر ساخرة
This is, you know, the movie poster.
هذا ملصق لفلم
Or we, a couple of weeks ago, designed a box set for The Talking Heads
أو منذ بضعة أسابيع صنعنا صندوق تصاميم لـ"الرؤوس المتكلمة"
where the happiness visualized on the cover definitely has, very much, a dark side to it.
حيث على الغلاف أخذ تصوير السعادة جانباً مظلماً بالفعل
Much, much more difficult is this, where the designs actually can evoke happiness --
الأصعب من ذلك بكثير هو التالي، حيث التصاميم التي تبعث السعادة
and I'm going to just show you three that actually did this for me.
وسأريكم ٣ فقط من التصاميم التي جعلتني سعيداً
This is a campaign done by a young artist in New York, who calls himself "True."
هذه حملة قام بها فنان شاب في نيويورك، يسمي نفسه "ترو" (بمعنى حقيقي)
Everybody who has ridden the New York subway system will be
أتوقع من كل من ركب قطارات الأنفاق في نيويورك
familiar with these signs?
بأن يتعرف على هذه العلامات
True printed his own version of these signs.
طبع "ترو" نسخته الخاصة من هذه التعليمات
Met every Wednesday at a subway stop with 20 of his friends.
كان يجتمع مع ٢٠ من أصدقائه في النفق كل أربعاء
They divided up the different subway lines and added their own version.
وينقسمون إلى خطوط القطارات المختلفة وينشرون نسختهم من الإشارات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this is one.
وهذه أيضاً
Now, the way this works in the system is that nobody ever looks at these signs.
الظريف في طريقة عمل هذه الحملة هو أنه لا أحد ينظر حقاً إلى هذه الإشارات
So you're
لذا فإنك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
you're really bored in the subway, and you kind of stare at something.
تجلس في القطار ويغمرك الملل، وتحدق في أي شيء
And it takes you a while until it actually --
ويستغرق منك لحظات إلى أن...
you realize that this says something different than what it normally says.
تدرك بأن هذه العلامة لا تحتوي على ما يفترض بها أن تحتوي عادةً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, that's, at least, how it made me happy.
أعني، هذا على الأقل ما جعلني سعيداً حيالها
Now, True is a real humanitarian.
نرى بأن "ترو" شخص إنساني بالفعل
He didn't want any of his friends to be arrested,
لم يرغب لأي من أصدقائه بأن يقبض عليهم ويحجزون
so he supplied everybody with this fake volunteer card.
لذا زود كل واحد منهم ببطاقة التطوع الزائفة هذه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And also gave this fake letter from the MTA to everybody --
كما أعطاهم هذه الرسالة الزائفة من الـ"إم تي ايه"...
sort of like pretending that it's an art project
ليتظاهروا بأنه نوع من المشاريع الفنية
financed by The Metropolitan Transit Authority.
المدعومة من قبل سلطات المرور للميترو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another New York project.
مشروع نيويوركي آخر
This is at P.S. 1 -- a sculpture that's basically a square room
هذه في بي أس ١... هي منحوتة لـ"جيمس توريل"
by James Turrell, that has a retractable ceiling.
عبارة عن غرفة مربعة ذات سقف قابل للسحب
Opens up at dusk and dawn every day.
تفتح في وقت الغسق والفجر كل يوم
You don't see the horizon.
لا يمكنك رؤية الأفق فيها
You're just in there, watching the incredible, subtle changes of color in the sky.
بل تقف هناك وبكل بساطة تنظر إلى التغير البارع للون السماء
And the room is truly something to be seen.
والغرفة جديرة بالمشاهدة حقاً
People's demeanor changes when they go in there.
تتغير طباع الناس أثناء وجودهم فيها
And, for sure, I haven't looked at the sky in the same way
وبالطبع، تغيرت نظرتي للسماء منذ
after spending an hour in there.
قضائي ساعة في هذه الغرفة
There are, of course, more than those three projects that I'm showing here.
هناك بالطبع أكثر من هذه الثلاثة مشاريع التي أريكم إياها الآن والتي جعلتني سعيداً
I would definitely say that observing Vik Muniz' "Cloud"
أعتبر مشاهدتي لمشروع "كلاود" (بمعنى غيمة) للفنان "فيك مونيز"
a couple of years ago in Manhattan for sure made me happy, as well.
منذ بضعة سنوات في مانهاتن أحد هذه المشاريع التي أسعدتني
But my last project is, again, from a young designer in New York.
لكن آخر مشروع أريكم إياه لمصمم شاب في نيويورك أيضاً
He's from Korea originally.
هو كوري الأصل
And he took it upon himself to print 55,000 speech bubbles --
وقد كلف نفسه عناء طباعة ٥٥٠٠٠ فقاعة حوار..
empty speech bubbles stickers, large ones and small ones.
ملصقات بشكل فقاعة حوار فارغة، بعضها كبير وبعضها صغير
And he goes around New York and just puts them, empty as they are, on posters.
وجاب أرجاء نيويورك ملصقاً الفقاعات الفارغة على الصور الملصقة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And other people go and fill them in.
وترك شرف ملئها للناس الآخرين
This one says, "Please let me die in peace."
هذه الفقاعة تقول: "أرجوك دعني أموت بسلام."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think that was --
أظن ذلك كان...
the most surprising to myself was that the writing was actually so good.
ما أدهشني حقاً هو أن الكتابة كانت جيدة جداً
This is on a musician poster, that says:
هذه على ملصق لفنان موسيقي، تقول:
"I am concerned that my CD will not sell more than 200,000 units
"إنني قلق من أن مبيعات أقراص أغانيي لن تصل أكثر من ٢٠٠٠٠٠ وحدة
and that, as a result, my recoupable advance
وبالتالي ستضيع فرصة
from my label will be taken from me,
استردادي لمال التعويض
after which, my contract will be cancelled,
ومن ثم سيتم إلغاء عقدي
and I'll be back doing Journey covers on Bleecker Street."
وسأعود إلى عمل صفقات ترحالية في شارع "بليكر"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think the reason this works so well is because everybody involved wins.
أظن بأن سبب نجاح هذا المشروع هو أن كل من يتدخل يربح
Jee gets to have his project;
صاحب المشروع "جيي" ينفذ مشروعه
the public gets a sweeter environment;
يحصل الناس على بيئة مرحة
and different public gets a place to express itself;
وبعض الناس يحصلون على فرصة للتعبير عن أنفسهم
and the advertisers finally get somebody to look at their ads.
كما يحصل أصحاب الدعايات على من يركز انتباهه على دعاياتهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, there was a question, of course, that was on my mind for a while:
حسناً، لدي هذا التساؤل الذي يراودني منذ فترة:
You know, can I do more of the things that I like doing in design
هل لي بأن أعمل أكثر على ما أحب عمله
and less of the ones that I don't like to be doing?
وأعمل أقل على مال لا أحبه في مجال التصميم؟
Which brought me back to my list making --
وهذا التساؤل يرجعني إلى قائمتي..
you know, just to see what I actually like about my job.
لأرى ما الذي يعجبني حقاً في عملي
You know, one is: just working without pressure.
وذلك التالي: أولاً العمل بدون ضغوطات
Then: working concentrated, without being frazzled.
ثانياً: العمل بتركيز، بدون النضوب
Or, as Nancy said before, like really immerse oneself into it.
أو كما قالت نانسي مرة، بأن تنغمس في العمل
Try not to get stuck doing the same thing --
وحاول بألا تعلق نفسك بفعل نفس الشيء مراراً..
or try not get stuck behind the computer all day.
أو بأن تعلق وراء جهاز الحاسب طول اليوم
This is, you know, related to it: getting out of the studio.
ثالثاً: الخروج من الستوديو
Then, of course, trying to, you know, work on things
وأخيراً: بالطبع محاولة العمل على أشياء
where the content is actually important for me.
ذات محتوى مهم بالنسبة لي
And being able to enjoy the end results.
والقدرة على الاستمتاع بالنتائج الأخيرة
And then I found another list in one of my diaries that actually contained
كما أنني عثرت في أحدى مذكراتي على قائمة تنص بالأشياء
all the things that I thought I learned in my life so far.
التي تعلمتها من الحياة حتى الآن
And, just about at that time, an Austrian magazine called and asked
وحينها كنت قد تلقيت اتصالاً من مجلة نمساوية يسألونني
if we would want to do six spreads -- design six spreads
إذا كنت أريد عمل ٦ فواصل... تصميم ٦ فواصل
that work like dividing pages between the different chapters in the magazine?
لصفحات المجلة لتقسيم الفصول المختلفة في المجلة
And the whole thing just fell together.
وسار كل شيء بشكل تلقائي
So I just picked one of the things that I thought I learned --
لذا اخترت أحد هذه الأشياء التي تعلمتها..
in this case, "Everything I do always comes back to me" --
في هذا التصميم: كل ما أفعله دائماً يعود بنتائجه علي..
and we made these spreads right out of this.
وصنعنا هذه الفواصل بناءً على ما تحتويه قائمتي
So it was: "Everything
لذا كان بهذا الشكل: كل
I do
ما أفعله
always
دائماً
comes
يعود
back
بنتائجه
to me."
علي
A couple of weeks ago, a
منذ بضعة أسابيع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
French company asked us to design five billboards for them.
طلبت منا شركة فرنسية بأن نصمم ٥ إعلانات خارجية لها
Again, we could supply the content for it.
مرة أخرى قررت بأنه يمكنني الاستفادة من قائمتي
So I just picked another one.
لذا اخترت جملة أخرى
And this was two weeks ago.
وهذا كان منذ أسبوعين
We flew to Arizona -- the designer who works with me, and myself --
سافرنا إلى أريزونا.. أنا والمصمم الذي يعمل معي...
and photographed this one.
وصورنا هذه
So it's: "Trying
بهذا الشكل: محاولة
to look
الظهور
good
بشكل جيد
limits
يحد
my life."
من حياتي
And then we did one more of these.
وقمنا بالمزيد من هذا النمط
This is, again, for a magazine, dividing pages.
هذه مرة أخرى لمجلة، لتقسيم الصفحات
This is: "Having" --
كالتالي: التحلي...
this is the same thing;
هنا نفس الشيء..
it's just, you know, photographed from the side.
فقط من زاوية مختلفة
This is from the front.
وهذه من الأمام
Then it's: "guts."
ثم: بالجرأة
Again, it's the same thing -- "guts" is just the same room, reworked.
مرة أخرى، نفس الكلمة.. "بالجرأة" مكونة في هذه الغرفة، بإعادة ترتيب
Then it's: "always
بعدها: دائماً
works out."
يعود بالنفع
Then it's "for," with the light on.
ثم هذه "علي" مع الإضاءة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it's "me."
وبعدها "شخصياً"
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)